Richard J. Neutra Papers
Richard J. Neutra Papers
1940-1966
Neutra, Richard Joseph, 1892-1970.
7 linear ft.
Papers of the American architect, born in Austria. Outgoing correspondence only, including drafts and revisions of letters of Neutra and of the Richard J. Neutra Institute (1940-1966); writings, including essays, lectures, speeches, and notes; audiorecordings. Writings, arranged chronologically, form a journal of ideas for lectures and articles, as well as writings on specific projects, and on the business of Neutra's architectural firm and of the Richard J. Neutra Institute. Also, a filmed interview with Neutra.
150125
Biographical History
Richard J. Neutra (1892-1970) was an Austrian-American architect. Born in Vienna, Austria, he studied under Adolf Loos at the Technische Hochschul and was influenced by Otto Wagner. He worked in the studio of Erich Mendelsohn in Germany from 1921-1922, then in 1923 moved to the United States (he became a United States citizen in 1929).
Neutra worked briefly for Frank Lloyd Wright before moving to California, where he opened his own practice in Los Angeles, the Richard J. Neutra Institute. (His son, with whom Neutra worked later in his career, maintains the office today as the Richard and Dion Neutra Architecture / Neutra Institute for Survival Through Design.) In addition to numerous private homes in California Neutra's works include the Airman Memorial Chapel at Miramar Naval Air Station, the Hall of Records in Los Angeles, the Orange County Courthouse in Santa Ana, the Germological Institute of America in Brentwood, and the Bewobau Housing Colony in Waldorf, Germany.
He was known for taking pains to ascertain the real needs of his clients, no matter the size of the job in question, rather than attempting to impose his own artistic vision on a project. Writing in Sunset magazine in 1943, Neutra explained that the success or "livability" of a house could be measured by how much living could be enjoyed in every part of it each hour of the day. A proponent of a modern style centered on the integration of buildings with their natural surroundings, Neutra wrote and spoke extensively on his architectural philosophy.
Neutra collaborated successfully with a series of partners including his wife, Dione; his protege, Robert Alexander; and his son, Dion. His autobiography, Life and Shape, was published in 1962. Two collections of his essays, letters and diaries were published posthumously, in 1986 and 1989.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1940 to 1966, the Richard J. Neutra Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, drawings, memorabilia, recordings, and writings of the Austrian-born American architect (1892-1970). Predominantly writings and recordings of his lectures and speeches, the collection illuminates Neutra's ideas on architecture, design, and planning.
Biographical material consists of contributions written by Neutra himself as well as by his wife Dione and his sons Raymond and Dion.
Correspondence includes drafts and revisions of outgoing letters of Neutra and of the Neutra Institute.
Drawings consists of original architectural perspectives for the Mymensinch University Convocation Hall and for the Orange County Court House, and photographic reproductions of some sketches by Neutra.
An assortment of news clippings, photostats, and pamphlets constitute Memorabilia. There is also a 16mm film of an interview with Neutra. The film has been copied onto video and both the original and the VHS copy are included in the collection.
Recordings contains audiorecordings of Neutra's lectures, speeches, talks, presentations, etc.
Writings encompasses essays, speeches and notes. Essays include published and unpublished articles by Neutra and pamphlets issued by the Richard J. Neutra Institute; speeches include both lectures and addresses. Neutra's notes form a journal of ideas for lectures and articles as well as writings on specific projects (Orange County Court House, Tower of Hope, VDL House, West Pakistan University), and on the business of the architectural firm, foundation, and institute that were founded by and named for him.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are first arranged alphabetically by type; speeches (both lectures and addresses) and essays are then arranged alphabetically by the title supplied by Neutra while Neutra's notes are arranged by date.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of noted architects. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Neutra, Richard Joseph, 1892-1970.; Richard J. Neutra and Associates.; Richard J. Neutra Institute.; Architects -- United States.; Architectural design.; Architectural firms.; Architectural practice.; Architecture -- United States.; Architecture -- Environmental aspects.; Architecture -- Human factors.; Architecture -- Psychological aspects.; Architecture -- Study and teaching.; Architecture, American.; Architecture, Domestic.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; Art -- Philosophy.; Austrian Americans.; City planning -- United States.; International style (Architecture) -- United States.; 16mm (photographic film size); Audiotapes.; Sound recordings.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Interviews.; Lectures.; Notes (documents); Speeches (documents); Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, circa 1940-1966; undated; 9 folders (Box 1)
- Drawings
  - Original architectural drawings, Mymensinch University, Orange County Court House (Box 4)
  - Reproductions (photographs) (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, miscellaneous printed material (Box 4)
  - Interviews
    - Television Interview with Stuart A. Batt, News Editor KFMB Ch. 8, 4-17-1959; neutra_rj_137; from 16mm film. Re: UCLA exhibition and R. Neutra's lecture San Diego Museum of Fine Arts; VHS; running time 120 (Box 8)
    - Television Interview with architect Richard J. Neutra, by Stuart A. Batt, News Editor KFMB -TV, Channel 8 (V-039), 4-17-1959; neutra_rj_138; from 16mm film. re: UCLA exhibition and R. Neutra's lecture San Diego Museum of Fine Arts; VHS; running time 120 (Box 8)
    - Television Interview with architect Richard J. Neutra, by Stuart A. Batt, News Editor KFMB -TV, Channel 8, 4-17-1959; neutra_rj_139; re: UCLA exhibition and R. Neutra's lecture San Diego Museum of Fine Arts; accompanied by copy of shipping package, original shipping package is in Box 8; 16mm film
- Recordings
  See also Interviews, above.
  - 20 Minutes of S.T.D. John O’Loudon, 03/12/1954; neutra_rj_007; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 20:00 (Box 5)
  - A.I.A. Athletic Club L.A., 07/10/1956; lecture by RJN; neutra_rj_032; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - A.I.A. Chicago Chap. June Dinner Meeting, neutra_rj_049; note on tape: To be returned after transportation; note on box: Cannot be transcribed; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - A.I.A. Convention, Yosemite; Discussion by RJN with Torraja for students of architecture, 10/22/1960; neutra_rj_111; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - An architect views a new world, 03/15/1957; neutra_rj_047; Architectural Panel; not transcribed as of 4/27/57; illegible information on box; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Architects Religion, 07/31/1960; neutra_rj_106; Lecture, Valley Unitarian Church; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
    First reel starting with reading by Neutra of excerpts from his book “Survival through Design” followed by two songs, accompanied on the cello and sung by Dione Neutra: Rispetto from Tuscany, 17th century Italian Ballade and Josef, liber Josef mein, 14th century German song. Rest of first reel and Side 2: Discussion between Richard and Raymond Neutra about his choosing a profession and what advice his father can offer him based on his own life.
  - Architectural Panel, 04/12/1963; lecture by RJN; neutra_rj_048; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Architecture and Prophesy, 03/24/1954; neutra_rj_008; Assistance League; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Architecture Today, 12/07/1958; neutra_rj_074; lecture at UCLA Schoneberg Hall; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Architecture: A Human Issue, 11/26/1957; neutra_rj_059; lecture given in Cincinnati, Ohio; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Architecture: A Human issue, 11/02/1960; neutra_rj_112; lecture, Mary Baldwin College; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - Architektur Aufnahme H. J. Grob, 10/24/1956; neutra_rj_045; Lecture: Baven, ein Menschliches problem; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Art and Science in Architecture Rembrandt Club, Pomona College Claremont, 06/20/1955; neutra_rj_018; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - The Arts: A human value in a scientific age, 02/05/1961; neutra_rj_114; lecture at San Fernando College; note on tape, "tape recorded by own Ampex tape recorder"; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - The Arts: A human value in a scientific age, 02/05/1961; neutra_rj_115; Reel 2; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - The Arts: A human value in a scientific age, 02/05/1961; neutra_rj_116; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - The Arts: A human value in a scientific age, 02/05/1961; neutra_rj_117; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - Aspen Conference, 06/29/1954; neutra_rj_017; continues on entire reel; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - [Aspen Conference] Lecture at the International Institute of Design, 06/29/1954; neutra_rj_016; recorded by Stanley Tonkel; second side of this reel is the continuation of the first side; recording is concluded on the first side of reel II; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Autobiographical Material Tape #2, 11/22/1957; neutra_rj_057; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
    RJN’s experiences in foreign countries; Learning through the questions that are asked; Interviews by Dr. Mac Masters, Los Angeles Examiner
  - Autobiographical Montenegro 1st World War, neutra_rj_034; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Autobiographical Siegfrid’s Doctor and Clinical Experience in Architecture and Medicine, neutra_rj_035; 2nd half continuation of A-1; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Autobiographical; Cusco Jail; Macao Church Ruin; Chinese Village, 08/1956; neutra_rj_036; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Barbara Morgan, 07/12/1957; neutra_rj_058; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Before Museum Member, 05/02/1958; neutra_rj_065; lecture, American Association of Museums; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Ben Hunter Interview with Richard J. Neutra, 11/12/1953; neutra_rj_003; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Biloxi Speech, 09/01/1953; neutra_rj_001; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 0:30:00 (Box 5)
  - Biloxi Speech, 09/01/1953; neutra_rj_002; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 0:30:00 (Box 5)
  - Cal Tech Lecture, 11/20/1958; neutra_rj_127; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - California Architecture, Past, Present, and Future, 03/12/1960; neutra_rj_098; luncheon talk, Unior Wilshire Ebelle Club; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 0:28:00 (Box 12)
  - Cavin Interview, 06/01/1955; neutra_rj_029; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - The Challenge of Design Conceptions and Misconceptions, 07/21/1954; neutra_rj_010; Recorded at U.C.L.A.; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 30:00 (Box 5)
  - The Creative Process in Architecture, 11/4/1953, 11/14/1953; neutra_rj_004; To Hacker Foundation; note on box: Both tracks have been transcribed; First track title illegible; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 0:22:29 (Box 5)
  - Charley McCarthy, 01/30/1955; neutra_rj_020; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Cross of Merit Award by Pres. Heuss; Speech by General Consul, Reply by RJN, 07/1959; neutra_rj_089; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Dr. Hertz Home, 1955; neutra_rj_021; transcribed (both sides) April 14, 1955; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Drucksache Einschreiben - Luftpost, neutra_rj_125; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - Dusseldorf Theater, 11/01/1959; neutra_rj_094; Mr. Neutra translating notes on a theater designed for Dusseldorf; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - Early Sunrise Thoughts, 02/13/1959; neutra_rj_081; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - European and American University Conversation With Fred Mayer, Albert Werner, 08/22/1957; neutra_rj_055; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Explanation by RJN of what he wants to achieve with autobiography, as recorded with Mr. Carlisle, N.Y.C., 10/02/1960; neutra_rj_110; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - First Conference on the R. J. N. [Richard Joseph Neutra] Movie Picture, 05/09/1957; neutra_rj_046; R. J. Neutra; G. Sernebiad; E. Schneider; V. Traub; L. Young; Nagel; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Garden Grove Meeting, 01/22/1959; neutra_rj_080; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Glendale College, 11/13/1959; neutra_rj_093; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - How to frustrate creativity, 07/1959; neutra_rj_088; interview with Charlotte Buhler; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - The Impact of Science on Your Life [part 1], 12/18/1958; neutra_rj_076; speech, Naval Civil Engineering Lab, Port Hueneme, California; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - The Impact of Science on Your Life [part 2], 12/18/1958; neutra_rj_077; speech, Naval Civil Engineering Lab, Port Hueneme, California; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Int. Theater colloquium RJN’s physiological ideas on theater and spectator, 11/28/1960; neutra_rj_113; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - Interview by Dr. Mac Masters, Los Angeles Examiner, 11/22/1957; neutra_rj_056; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Interview Dr. Neutra, 05/1955; neutra_rj_030; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Interview for Cavalcade of Books, 02/15/1954; neutra_rj_005; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Interview for Mrs. Carl Samuelson, 04/28/1957; neutra_rj_050; for city college paper on Richard Neutra; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Interview Ostorr. Fernsehen, neutra_rj_122; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - Interview over radio Munich, 1960; neutra_rj_109; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - interview with Mr. Sonnenberg; text of book to be edited by J. Carlos on philosophy and attitude of the architect to clients and others, 05/25/1960; neutra_rj_102; to be used in Arch. Engineering News; includes letter to Carlos; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - Interview, DN with Miss Johanne Schmidt, Munich. RJN as seen by wife, 03/1959; neutra_rj_084; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Introduction UCLA Exhibit opening St. Barbara, 01/12/1959; neutra_rj_079; lecture Santa Barbara Museum Library; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
    Opening of one man show UCLA. Speaks how many helpers an architect has. Passion of empathy for clients. How architecture is experienced through many portals. Visions, explains Greek idea of heaven etc. Much audience laughter. Tape includes description of slides. African landscapes buildings, Residences Brown, Hammerman, Kronish, Troxell, Perkins, Steller, Rados Chase, Slavin, Tremaine, Kaufman
  - Is Planning Possible, 04/10/1959; neutra_rj_085; conversation with editor Elizabeth Emmanuel; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Kingsley Art Club, neutra_rj_023; transcribed April 13, 1955; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - KTIM San Rafael: Kitty Oppenheimer interview with Richard Neutra, 06/20/1957; neutra_rj_052; includes a note; crossed-out information on the box reads: "To: KFBK Sacramento, Calif."; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Left to Right and Back again No. 1, neutra_rj_051; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - Life and Human Habitat, State College, Ames, Iowa, 10/23/1958; neutra_rj_071; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Lifetime should be the amortization period of a good house, 02/27/1959; neutra_rj_083; lecture to Harvard Club; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Long Beach Rotarians”What Will The Neighbors Think?” Beckstrand Introducing, neutra_rj_039; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Los Feliz Forum Lecture Part 1, 08/10/1955; neutra_rj_024; transcribed; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Los Feliz Forum Lecture Part 2, 08/10/1955; neutra_rj_025; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Los Feliz Forum Lecture Part 3, 08/10/1955; neutra_rj_026; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Main Address, 05/31/1955; neutra_rj_031; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Man in his organic setting, 12/03/1958; neutra_rj_073; lecture given to landscape architects; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Man the Measure, 09/30/1958; neutra_rj_066; lecture, UCLA Scripps Institute of Oceanography; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Man the measure - Radical Roots in Architecture, 11/20/1958; neutra_rj_072; lecture, California Institute of Technology; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - The mission of housing Americans, 08/19/1960; neutra_rj_108; lecture, Stanford University; keynote address at Architect and Homebuilder Design Clinic; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 13)
  - The most precious material, 10/19/1962; neutra_rj_123; lecture, Zagreb, Yugoslavia; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - Neutra - Library, neutra_rj_041; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - A New Shape To Our World, 02/18/1957; lecture before the "Seakchers," Clarion Hall; neutra_rj_042; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - North Carolina State College RJN Seminar Part 1, 12/01/1957; neutra_rj_060; talks with students on carious subjects of a week seminar; Raleigh, N.C.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State College RJN Seminar Part 2, 12/01/1957; neutra_rj_061; talks with students on carious subjects of a week seminar; Raleigh, N.C.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State College RJN Seminar Part 3, 12/01/1957; neutra_rj_062; talks with students on carious subjects of a week seminar; Raleigh, N.C.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State College RJN Seminar Part 4, 12/01/1957; neutra_rj_063; talks with students on carious subjects of a week seminar; Raleigh, N.C.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State College RJN Seminar Part 5, 12/01/1957; neutra_rj_064; talks with students on carious subjects of a week seminar; Raleigh, N.C.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Notre Dame Reels 1 and 2, neutra_rj_037; re-recording; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - [Notre Dame] Reels 3 and 4, neutra_rj_038; re-recording; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Ojai Happy Valley, 03/01/1955; neutra_rj_022; transcribed April 12, 1955; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Oklahoma State Univ., 11/03/1959; neutra_rj_091; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Painted Desert Project; Urbanization - Overlap of Territories, 05/08/1960; neutra_rj_100; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - The Place of the Human Being in Today’s Progess, 02/26/1960; neutra_rj_097; lecture, Pierce College; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 0:31:00 (Box 12)
  - Pomeroy Consultation, 12/1958; neutra_rj_075; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - R.J. Neutra discusses with a student the problems of designing Constance Perkins House, neutra_rj_067; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - The Religion of An Architect, 05/22/1960; neutra_rj_101; lecture, First Unitarian Church of Los Angeles; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
    See also neutra_rj_096 and neutra_rj_101 neutra_rj_106, which may be related to this.
  - Richard J. Neutra Institute, 04/21/1963; neutra_rj_120; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - Richard Neutra Talk Des Moines Art Center, 10/14/1958; neutra_rj_068; Part 1; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Richard Neutra Talk Des Moines Art Center, 10/14/1958; neutra_rj_069; Part 2; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Is Art Provable?, 04/17/1957; RJN lecture at Art Educators Convention; neutra_rj_044; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - RJN's interview with Uruguayan Architects, 05/31/1960; neutra_rj_103; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - The role of the architect in religion, 02/20/1960; neutra_rj_096; lecture, Southwest Conference to Unitarian Ministers; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - Roots of Calif. Arch. Summer 1956, neutra_rj_033; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - S.T.D. Art Directors Club, 06/11/1954; neutra_rj_009; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 60:00 (Box 5)
  - Sad Evening Thoughts, 12/12/1959; neutra_rj_095; Neutra speaks about his collaborators and teamwork; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - San Francisco Museum, 12/06/1955; neutra_rj_027; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 12/06/1955; neutra_rj_028; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Santa Barbara Lecture Part 1, neutra_rj_053; Dr. Baer, Art Department; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Santa Barbara Lecture Part 2, neutra_rj_054; Dr. Baer, Art Department; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 9)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #1, neutra_rj_129; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #2, neutra_rj_130; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #3, neutra_rj_131; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #4, neutra_rj_132; letters: 4 in German, 2 in English, last letter incomplete; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #5, neutra_rj_133; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #7, neutra_rj_134; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt [#8?], neutra_rj_136; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Santa Barbara Speech Dictabelt #9, neutra_rj_135; Grooved Dictabelt (Box 8)
  - Sayewild Art Conference, 08/25/1954; neutra_rj_013; partly transcribed on 11/24/1954; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 15:00 (Box 5)
  - Second part of Symposium: Mrs. Weigle, neutra_rj_015; after a port of introduction, there was no sound on tape; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Sendewagen Tape Copy for RIchard Neutra, 01/01/1954; neutra_rj_011; note on box: S.D.A. #199; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Sum and Substance, 03/02/1963; neutra_rj_124; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 14)
  - Survival, 02/13/1959; neutra_rj_082; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Survival Through Design, Verdugo Hills Art Association, 06/24/1955; neutra_rj_019; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 6)
  - Talk to Raymond’s Class, 07/31/1959; neutra_rj_090; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Talk with collaborators about checking working plans and how to draw plan that contractors understand, 01/02/1959; neutra_rj_078; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Theory of School Design, 07/08/1954; neutra_rj_014; Dr. Seagers; Indiana Un; 1st side transcribed 11/05/1954; 2nd side transcribed 11/08/1954; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Tulsa Engineers, 05/08/1959; lecture by RJN; neutra_rj_087; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Unitarian Church Architecture Friendly to Mankind, 03/07/1954; neutra_rj_006; note on box: Transcribed 10/19/1956; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 60:00 (Box 5)
  - Unitarian Church San Diego, 04/16/1959; neutra_rj_086; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Univ of Oklahoma, 11/03/1959; neutra_rj_092; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 11)
  - Utility - Or More?, 05/19/1960; neutra_rj_104; lecture, University of Utah; Annual Dinner Meeting of Utah Chapter A.I.A. and Arch. Dept. of Utah University; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - Voice of America: The city of the future, 05/08/1957; neutra_rj_040; German interview with Walter Ducloux for broadcast in West Germany; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 7)
  - Washington University Assembly Series Richard J. Neutra, F.A.I.A. “Man, the Measure”, 10/22/1958; neutra_rj_070; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 10)
  - Who is the Client of the Architect, 04/30/1960; neutra_rj_099; Awards Banquet, California State Polytechnic College, San Luis Obispo, "With gratitude and compliments!"; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - World Reconstruction, 04/24/1960; neutra_rj_105; Lecture, Chapman College, Orange, Cal.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)
  - Yale Lecture; Department of Architecture; School of Fine Arts, 04/15/1957; neutra_rj_043; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
  - [no title], neutra_rj_012; label reads "Tape Copy for Richard Neutra" and S.D.A. #201; Auditioned; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - [no title], neutra_rj_107; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 12)